<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine and moral discourses on divers subjects</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36167</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12755048</idno>
  <idno type="VID">93397</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240958628</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1715</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32790</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12755048</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36167)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93397)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1033:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine and moral discourses on divers subjects</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 95 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Keble,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:93397:1"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March <hi>30th. 1693.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guil. Lancaster.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93397:1"/>
            <p>DIVINE AND MORAL DISCOURSES ON Divers Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Keble</hi> at the <hi>Turks Head</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93397:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93397:2"/>
            <head>TO THE QUEEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THese Papers are Humbly Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, by Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Dutiful and Obedient Subject</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:93397:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93397:3"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> OF the Christian Religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on <hi>Page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Of the Benefits of Patience in particular <hi>Page 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Of Divine Love. <hi>Page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Of Mortification. <hi>Page 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Of Charity. <hi>Page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Of Humility. <hi>Page 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Of Prudence. <hi>Page 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Of the Advantages of the Great in respect of Religion and it's Rewards. <hi>Page 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Of true Wisdom. <hi>Page 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Of a Virtuous Obstinacy. <hi>Page 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Of Peace. <hi>Page 70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Of Contemplation and the Active Life. <hi>Page 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Of Prayer. <hi>Page 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14:</hi> Of the many and Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting
<pb facs="tcp:93397:4"/>Christianities in Christendom. <hi>Page 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Prayers. <hi>Page 89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> Thanksgiving. <hi>Page 92</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="collection_of_maxims">
            <pb facs="tcp:93397:4"/>
            <head>Short Expressions of Comfort.</head>
            <p>HE who loves Beauty, and to be beloved again; let him love God, who is the greatest Beauty and the greatest Lover.</p>
            <p>He who loves riches, let him love God, who is an Infinite Treasure of riches.</p>
            <p>He who is Ambitious, and loves honour, let him love God the Fountain of honour.</p>
            <p>He who loves pleasure, let him love God, at whose right hand there are pleasures for evermore, and who is himself an Infinite Fountain of Joy.</p>
            <p>He who loses his Soul, has lost all.</p>
            <p>He who secures his Soul, has se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd all.</p>
            <p>One moment in Heaven will satisfie for all that we have suffer'd on earth.</p>
            <p>The condition on which the
<pb facs="tcp:93397:5"/>happiness of Heav<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n is promis'd us, is, that we will be happ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on earth, by living acccording to virtue.</p>
            <p>God will protect us, and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port us, and reward us, in his own Service.</p>
            <p>None are Wise, or Great, or Happy, but the virtuous.</p>
            <p>Virtue is a Nobler thing then a Crown.</p>
            <p>Nothing is wit or parts, but virtue and happiness, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so dull, and stupid, and weak, as vice, and misery, let the man be nere so pert, or nere so grave.</p>
            <p>Nothing can befriend us but virtue, Nothing can touch or hurt us but sin.</p>
            <p>A good life is the best sence in the world; and vice is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Insence and irreason in nature.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93397:5"/>
            <head>Of the Christian Religion in general.</head>
            <p>'TIS certain there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so charming, so advantageous as the practice of the Christian Religion, while it secures to us all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this Life, and of that to come; that purifies our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and adorns our Souls, that raises our Hope, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames our Love, and rejoyces our Faith, and banishes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spair by the infinite Love and Mercy of the Holy Trinity, that attends this holy practice, which disperses our Sorrows and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>averts our Griefs, but swells our Joys, and enflames our Tryumph, and chafes our Hope, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scends the Angels, and mixes Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with human Life, and drowns the World in a Deluge of Joys,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93397:6"/>and an Ocean of Comforts, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing all with unspeakable sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions and pleasure.</p>
            <p>If unspeakable joys can Charm, if everlasting hopes can move, if extasies as long as Eternity and endless Rapture can prevail with us to love our own happiness, and befriend our own Beings, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not choose but be in love with Religion, and charm'd with Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, the sure means of so much Tryumph, and such large Joys, that are bigger then our Notions, and stretch themselves over all Eternity, and hold out as long as God: And now what can we wish for more then Religion assures us of? if happiness can provoke us, here it is to be had; if our own desires can satisfie us, here we shall enjov them and more, there is nothing that's pleasant or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable but shall flow in upon us in the fullest measures, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow our souls for ever.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93397:6"/>
            <p> The most unbounded fancy will find it self exceeded by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which gives beyond what that can imagine, and surpasses it's most heated desires, and instead of contracting, it enlarges our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, and gives them more than satisfaction; it entertains our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son with just and equal Objects, and feeds it with rational and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per satisfactons, and always keeps in it's view, that which is lushious, great and divine, pure and Noble, firm and Everlasting; in Religion no labour shall be lost, no sorrow shall be able to oppress us, no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure shall abuse us, no vanity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>snare us, but we shall be wise for our selves, and wise for ever, we shall be useful to others by the greatest charity of our devotions, if we are poor, and by the lesser charity of our almes too, if we are rich; we shall be always employ'd to the height of our beings, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert the perfection of our Natures,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93397:7"/>and act above them in the Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Grace.</p>
            <p>None of our actions shall be lost, or recoyle with mischief upon us, we shall be strangers to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusions that attend on pride, and escape the Storms of passion, and the racks of Envy, and the disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Lust, and the toils, and the labours, and the precipices; and after all the follie of Ambition, and a Sad, a foolish, and an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Greatness; and sit down in the peace, and wisdom, and quiet, and joys, and security, if not in the transports of a fair, an easie, and a wise happiness at present, and a ravishing hope that can't be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed but by uneasie joys, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of happiness, and convulsions of pleasure, and Agonies of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
            <p>And now who can employ his labours wisely any where else? where the income is no less then Infinite, and Eternal, in which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93397:7"/>Angels assist, and attend him; that Cloud of glorious Witnesses, who fan the Toils of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors and Martyrs, and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of the Laps'd and the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, with the brightest Joys, and peaceful Whispers.</p>
            <p>And whither should we now go for Happiness, but to Religion, the Mother of Satisfactions and Content, the Parent of Delight and Hope, of present Joy and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Immortality.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93397:8"/>
            <head>Of the Benefits of Patience in particular.</head>
            <p>WHoever considers the vast and eternal Rewards that are propos'd in the other Life, will soon be perswaded to believe, that all we can suffer in this Life is easie and little, joyn'd with the Assistances that are given us from Heaven for our support, and if we consider that we suffer for him who is Infinitely Beautiful, and loves as infinitely, and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Glorious, and is infinitely able to make us happy, and in finitely willing, our very miseries will be lushious and charming, and our Sufferings will be drown'd in Joys unspeakable and full of Glory. 'Twill be pleasant to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for so much Beauty, and his Will will always be charming, and his Love will always charm us: now whatever we do or suffer for an infinite Beauty, and an infinite
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93397:8"/>Love, cannot be without tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sports and extasies; the feigntings of Love, that turns all into joy and ravishment, into peace and consolation and the bigger joy will drown the lesser misery; the visits of Love, and the irruptions of Heaven, and the kindness of the supream Beauty, breaking in upon the Soul, will make every thing unspeakably charming and triumphant, such as no Humane Joys can equal, nor all the World is able to purchase; such as the <hi>Caesars</hi> never knew, nor the bloody Conqueror ever tasted, but such as the Martyrs have felt, and the Confessors enjoy'd, and have confessed they were greater then their pains, and harder to bear, and some of them have died of Love and Joys, who surviv'd all their torments and outliv'd their pains, but Love was stronger then Death, and overcame Life and it to, and carried them on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93397:9"/>its Flames to Eternal Triumphs and Glory, to behold that beauty face to face, whom they loved so much, and whose enjoyment they sought through Flames and Death, and at last obtained through the Interest of miseries and death, the unspeakable advantages that attend on Sufferings and Patience in a Religion that's lavish of Crowns and Rewards, and scatters Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Palms, and everlasting Glories amongst them that resist unto blood striving against Sin.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <head>Of Divine Love</head>
            <p>Nothing but Love can write of Love, 'tis all experience and joy, transport and Obedience, it comes from God, and returns to God, the Sovereign Beauty, the Infinite Lover, the source of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93397:9"/>and bounty, 'tis the height and quintessence of Religion, the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness of Angels, that that made the Worlds, and preserves them from ruin, that created, redeem'd, and sanctified Mankind; that Makes Religion Charming, and Duty pleasure, and Obedience Liberty; that refines the soul, and purifies the body, the great Enemy of Hypocrisie and Rebellion, that that makes us Noble and sincere, humble and Great, easie, reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and Constant, that enflam'd the Martyrs, and preserv'd the Confessors, 'tis that heaven that waits not for death, but mingles with this mortal life, and comes down upon it in showers of trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and illapses of joy, and tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous uneasie happinesses, that rend us with their greatness, that are fierce and violent, and act like Pangs and Agonies, and the Face of Heaven is covered with Tempests while the joy is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93397:10"/>too great for a Calm, and ferments into Storms and Violence.</p>
            <p>Oh Sacred Passion! Oh Divine Pain! Oh sweetest Pleasure! food of Angels! reward of Martyrs! consolation of the humble! how shall we be satisfied with thy delights! when shall we be transform'd into thee! when we have found thee, we have found Heaven, when we enjoy thee, we enjoy all things, even God himself; for God is Love, and he that dwelleth in love dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in God, and God in him; he is ravisht with Beauty, and filled with Love, and satisfied with Knowledge, and desires nothing more, but to love and suffer more for the infinite Beloved, to be always doing that that pleases him most and to be humble to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most, because, that pleases him most to adore his Beauty, and to imitate his Love, and to know his Will, and to perform it with ardour, and to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93397:10"/>hate his own, and to love Mankind, who bears the Image of the Infinite Beloved, and is still longing for the Beatifick and Eternal Vision, that grasps in it all Happiness, and draws after it all Joys, where millions of Angels are fixt in an everlasting extasie, and gaze, and love out eternal Ages, singing Hallelujahs, and Glory, and Love, to the Sovereign Beauty for ever and ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <head>Of Mortification.</head>
            <p>LEt no man pretend to love Pleasure that does not love the Practice of Mortification, both of Body and Mind, hence the Health, hence the Purity, hence the Beauty and the Joy of both. By this we conquer Earth, in order to the conquest of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by this we conquer our selves first, and then our Enemies, by it we resind all that's foolish and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93397:11"/>mischievous in the World, the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of Gluttony, and the deluges of Intemperance, and the vanity of Pride, and the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonableness of Covetousness, and the paleness of Envy, and the stupidity of Cunning, and the losses of Dishonesty, and the poverty of Oppression. It sets us quite above this World and all that's mortal or corruptible; and in order to clear the way to a firm, and pure, and lasting Happiness, it cuts off all the falsest Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to it, as Lust, and Ambition, Luxury, and Power, and fixes it in that that is spiritual and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting, fitted to the greatness and duration of the Soul, in Divine Love and Devotion, in Chastity, and forgiving injuries, in humility and a true Ambition, in Wisdom and Goodness, in Temperance and Generosity, in Patience and Crowns, in Faith and Everlasting Kingdoms, and makes us greater
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93397:11"/>then <hi>Caesars</hi> or Consuls, and gives us better Tryumphs, and chafes us to nobler Conquests; by it the Soul is raised to its true Glory, made wise and strong, noble and clean, active and ambitious, humble and great, discerns, pursues, and overtakes its interest, and seizes on Eternal Glories.</p>
            <p>And whoever considers the emptiness of the things of this World, how false and uncertain, how trifling and vain, how disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing and sad, will soon be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd that he can employ his time in nothing more advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then in subduing the Follies and Miseries of the World, and retrenching all that's hurtful to the Body and Soul, and bringing each to their proper nourishment and stint, and in effect, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification is nothing else but a cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off whatever is a hindrance or an enemy to our true Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and where is the harm or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93397:12"/>the loss in all this? by Temperance we cut off Dropsies and Fevers, and almost the whole list of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempers, that wait on our follies, and punish our excesses by Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the storms and the rages of an incens'd Pride, that's torn with affronts, and rack't with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and rive the miserable man that's subject to the merciless and Cruel distemper; and he that's loving and kind, escapes the whips and snakes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and consuming Malice, that live upon the blood, and feed on the very Vitals, and consume the spirits, and fret him into a Skelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and vex him to a Ghost.</p>
            <p>By Chastity we escape the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulsions, the pollutions, the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces, and the distempers of Lust, that Wars against the Soul that Enemy of it's Crown and Glory, that subdues i'ts beauty, and darkens it's faculties, and cloggs it's soar, and conceals Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93397:12"/>and overcasts the glorious prospect, and sullies all it's bright designs, that turns the Soul into body, and the body into Beast; and to conclude, Mortification, by which I mean that of the Soul as well as that of the body, is the removal of every misery, and the Introduction of every Joy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <head>Of Charity.</head>
            <p>WHoever is a Lover of himself, must be a Lover of this duty, that in the end tends so much to our own interest, tho that ought not to be our design; while I become my Brothers friend, I render God mine, and Heaven, and everlasting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are the unspeakable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of a charitable Religion, and he, who will not practice this duty, is resolv'd to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for himself, that is, he is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93397:13"/>resolved to manage his Interests without the blessing of God, or the assistance of his Neighbours, he will neither do good nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive good, he forsakes the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of Mankind, and is forsaken of Mankind, he will act by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and perish by himself, he will take care for one, and will be that one, the World will take no care at all of.</p>
            <p>He has rejected the best Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in Nature or Religion, that which makes Heaven and Earth happy, that by which the Angels are Angels, and that for want of which Devils are Devils, he has separated himself from the whole Creation, and excluded himself from the common Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the World, he has bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out from Society, and that Commonwealth, that ties the World, and sits a single Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Government by himself, and will prosper only from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93397:13"/>and by himself, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny regard to a common good, or a mutual assistance, he has divested himself of all the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a tender Humanity, and of that Love, without which no Man can be happy.</p>
            <p>But the Charitable Man on the other hand is good and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as an Angel, is acted by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Love, and differs little from the Angels, as he was made but a little lower than they, and comes as near the life of Heaven, as a mortal Body will let him, and acts by that principle which alone gives Happiness to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; he loves, and while he does so, is obliged to be happy, and his Soul is charm'd with the brightest pleasures, and the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Joys, and over flows with that passion, that is it self very joy, and the very life and heaven of the Soul, its greatest duty and its greatest reward; 'tis more than
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93397:14"/>ease and peace, 'tis positive hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, and a substantial pleasure, that makes every thing delightful and entertaining, that's good or innocent, and in that degree we converse with it, we converse with Heaven, and have reacht all the Perfection our Souls are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of in this Life, for there is nothing higher or happier than Love, for God himself is that excellent thing, by it he creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and rules the World, and wherever it is in its full perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is Heaven; this the Angels experience in their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries here below, while they come down with breasts flaming with Charity and Love, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Heaven with them, that is a boundless love to God and Man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93397:14"/>
            <head>Of Humility.</head>
            <p>HUmility is the Foundation of Religion, the Pillar of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, the security of a good Life, the Duty and the Wisdom of a Man, the terror of the Devil, the restorer of the Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the great Example of the Son of God. This is it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stores the broken Penitent, and and recovers the Laps'd, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures the Faithful, that puts Temptations to Flight, and the Tempter too, that charmes the Angels, and is admired by Men, and pleads with God, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains Heaven, and rescues from Eternal ruine.</p>
            <p>Is any Man Ambitious? Let him be Humble, and he shall be as great as he can desire: O may the same minde be in us all, which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93397:15"/>was also in Christ Jesus, who being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God, but made himself of no reputation, for which God also hath highly exalted him, there is nothing truely Great, but Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, or truely mean, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicable, and little, but Pride: though Humility descend to the bottom of the lowest Vallies, yet it rises to the utmost bounds of the everlasting Hills, crowning the Penitent and the Confessor with eternal Wreaths of Glory, and the Valley of tears becomes fruitful and glorious as the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of <hi>Eden,</hi> and from the River of Tears that issues thence, is the whole World refresht. Whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver would be truly wise, let him be truely humble and he shall be so. Whoever would be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy, let him be truely hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and he shall be so. Whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver would be secure from all evils
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93397:15"/>spiritual and temporal, let him be truly humble, and he shall be so; let him that loves peace love humility, for from pride on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cometh War; it avoids all things, it obtains all things, it guards, it comforts, it releives, it strengthens, and gives Palms and Crowns. The Angels wait upon't, and before it fly Legions and Millions of the Evil Spirits. Heaven is always open to it, and by it the vast ascent is rendred easie and safe, and the dangerous road of life, secure. The Eye, and the favour, and the Light of the countenance of God is always upon't, to rescue, to cherish, and to Crown all its sufferings, and contempts, and labours, it's persecutions and toils from the folly and the wickedness of men and Devils, and secures it's road to eternal Kingdoms, and to the flaming Courts of Glory, and to him, who for the joy that was set
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93397:16"/>before him, and for our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, endured the Cross, despising the shame, and is now set down at the right hand of God, and in the Majesty of the Father, exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that nature of ours in which he humbled himself above Heaven and Earth, and at whose Name the whole Creation bows.</p>
            <p>If this duty of humility were in it's full practice in the world, how great would be the peace of Mankind, how would Storms and Wars cease, Ambition and Revenge sleep, and the rage of the Conquerour, and the terrors of the Invader: This one Virtue would supply the use of Laws, and the necessity of Sanctions, would take away the Judge and the Executioner, the Officer, and an untimely death, the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressor and the Tyrant, and Peace and Love would administer the World, and Umpire all the differences in it, and Furv would
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93397:16"/>be no more; nor the Shield, nor the Sword, nor the Battle. The Tyrant and the Virgin, the Conqueror and the Infant, the King and the Helpless would Sit down in equal strengths and security, and the power of the Strong would be the guard and protection of the Weak, and the defence of the helpless and of the trembling Maid.</p>
            <p>To this duty would be owing all the happinesses and joys of friendship, and an unbroken Love of Mutual Offices, and Rival Services, which are all interrupted, broken, and disper'st by the quarrels, and exceptions of Pride, and an unsociable Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and a Malancholy Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by a Peevish Solitary Haughtiness, which is the bane of Society and happiness, and of all that's innocent or chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the World.</p>
            <p>By it the Trumpet and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93397:17"/>would be turn'd into the Pipe, and the Tabret, and the Harp; and the Shrieks of the Slain, and the Groans of the Battle, into the Songs of Virgins, and the Smiles of Peace. And the Panther would be a Lamb, and the Consul and the Admiral would quit the Seas and the Field, and cat the Bread of Peace, and drink the Wine of Love. And Armies would disperse, and Fleets would serve the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, for want of Cruel and Ambitious Leaders, of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgs</hi> and <hi>Tourvils,</hi> of <hi>Catanetts</hi> and <hi>Destrees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Humility would be owing all the Ease of Life, and undiffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of living happy, for Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity would add Greatness and Content, to that condition which the haughty Man can't live on, 'twould make us always thankful and Glad, and to find rest every where, and turn the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93397:17"/>Painful soar, and the weary Climbe into the easiness of a descent, and a Fall that's receiv'd on a Bed of Down, 'twould make the Servant as happy as the Lord, and by how much the more contented, by so much the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier. And in that degree that Ambition racks the mind, and Pride makes every thing trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome and uneasie, in the same degree does Humility make all quiet and Easie, and gives sleep to the Soul that was tortur'd with Ambition, and burst with Pride.</p>
            <p>It fixes the Man in his Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he seeks no farther, he would for his ease fall yet lower, but for a Crown would not rise higher, if he is constant to his wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and his happiness, and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. And there he safely beholds, and at a secure distance, the Rises and the Falls of the Ambitious man, his Rocks, his precipices,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93397:18"/>and his plunges, now hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the top of the craggy Precipice, then losing his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate hold falling down head long into the Abyss and bottom of infamy and despair, there wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his ruin.</p>
            <p>It makes all safe and firm about us as there is nothing lower, so there is nothing securer; 'tis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and constant, and as it has no floods, so it has no ebbs, 'tis a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness equally diffus'd over the face of life, and above all other du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Religion most secures to us the Favour and the protection of God, and is most remarkable in the Example, and precepts, and life of Christ, who descended from the highest Glory, to the lowest condition of humane nature; he himself has set us the vast coppy, and has liv'd before us that we should follow his Example and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and what can Kings or Emperors do greater then follow
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93397:18"/>so great a Leader, him by whom both the worlds were made, and was above all Scepters and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and yet took upon him the Form of a servant, and made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self of no reputation, and humbled himself even to the death of the Cross, who at the same time thought it no robbery to be equal with God. And what greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample can they propose to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and after his authority, what can be judg'd so truly great, as to be truly Humble, and like the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Jesus, who taught us by his life, and bought us with his death, who laid aside all his Glory and all his happiness for the salvation of man, and Oh that Mankind that was redeemed and saved with so much humility and conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scention, would imitate the great Example, and that none would think that mean, that was made great in the life of the Holy Jesus, and was the great Assistant towards our Salvation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93397:19"/>
            <head>Of Prudence.</head>
            <p>THis is so necessary a Virtue, that without it all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Virtues will quickly wither and decay, 'tis the Strength, and Band, and Guard, and Overseer of all the other virtues, without it we shall but do and undo, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence will put us as far back, as Zeal will set us forward. And here I shall relate a famous passage of <hi>Antony</hi> the famous <hi>Hermit</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that Angel of the Desert, and of whom St. <hi>Hierome</hi> writes with so much praise, and so much admiration, while he himself for four years together led that life, accompanied only by Angels and wild Beasts, and Prayers, and Fasts, and Hymns, and sacred Books, and probably had spent his whole life in those Deserts of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93397:19"/>whither he retir'd from the world, to live in a clearer view of Heaven, and in stronger Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations of virtue, and safer from the incursions and Devasta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Enemy the world, and in a closer fellowship with Angels, had not the Arrian Inquisitors forc'd him from his Retreat, and from those Quires of Angels with which he says, he sometimes though thimself surrounded, and disturbed his peaceful Empire, and his lonesome Reign.</p>
            <p>The passage is this, Many Holy Men assembled themselves once at the Cell of great <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony,</hi> to advise with him what were the most efficacious and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure means to arrive at the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Holy Life, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Virtue and Happiness: and when the debate had lasted from Evening almost to Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, each discoursing earnestly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93397:20"/>and long on the subject, in ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to discover the shortest and the safest road to happiness and an entire Virtue, and when each had delivered his different Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, one Judging it chiefly to consist in fasting and watching, while by these means the mind being purified, and cleans'd, and rais'd, it might the more easily unite it self to God, others plac't it in an entire throwing off the World, and all its interests, and cares, and interruptions, that so the mind being loose and disingag'd from those cloggs and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that hang like weights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her and keep her down from her true happiness, may with a quicker flight, and a freer soar reach its long'd for happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and perfection. Others the Desart, and an Immence Solitude, and the Sacred Horrors of the Wilderness, and an unbroken Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93397:20"/>where the Soul has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else to do, but seize di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly on its happiness, by strong and perfect Contemplations, by pure and constant prayer, and an uninterrupted Holiness, and a Heaven broke in upon Life, clear'd from all the stormes and shipwracks, the dangers and the impertinencies, the cruel mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and more cruel pleasures, the false joys and the sincere sorrows, of a miserable, uncertain, and confus'd world, thats made up of noise, and shew, and ruin. Others said it lay chiefly in Charity and good Works, and that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour seems in a manner to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the practice of this Duty, and when most of the night had been spent in delivering their several Judgments, on this great subject, <hi>Intulit demum Beatus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius,</hi> at last the Blessed <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93397:21"/>the Angel of the Desart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, I grant says he, that all those things you have nam'd are not onely Good and Holy, but also highly necessary to be practis'd by all that seek the Glories of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, but the many miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and the sad and mournful ruin of many great Men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly and lately, and within our own knowledge will no way al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me to give any of them the chief place on this occasion, for have we not known several that after having exceeded in these du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that have fasted themselves to Skellitons, and having given them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves wholly up to prayer and to watching, even to the exceeding the powers of Nature, to Hymns and Praises, and reacht the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Perfection of Humanity, and Charity, that they were the wonder and admiration of all Men, and a Glorious Spectacle to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93397:21"/>Angels and to Men, yet all of a suddain, and to the Terror and Horror of the Desart; we have seen them after so long and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us a Course, after the Labours, and the Improvements, and the Victories, and the Wonders of so many years, when we had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenc'd them as Angels, whose Lives they had so nearly coppied, and who seem'd to us, to be at the same time in Heaven and the body too, yet by horrid and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable delusions, and by the stratagems of the subtle and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visible Enemy, all of a suddain, thrown down from the heights of Glory and Happiness, to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bottom and Abyss of Ruin and loss, and the Glorious Life that had been carried on for so many years, and with so much admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and even to a very old age by some, (Witness Old <hi>Heron</hi> the Hermit, the Glory and the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93397:22"/>of this Desart, whom you have all admir'd and wept) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguisht in a hydeous and an ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing death, all blotted and spoild by miserable delusions, and the wiles of the dark and execrable Foe. Therefore the way to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover what that is that best pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes, and perfects, and Secures our Religion and Passage to God and a better World, is to find out the cause of the ruin and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage of these Great Men. 'tis certain that the want of discretion alone was the utter loss and ruin of them, which directs us always to keep the middle path, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void extreams of both hands, not to exceed in Virtue it self, or go too fast to Heaven it self, but to do Justice to Nature and the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which else, one time or other, will have their Arrears in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses of a scandalouss intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Debauch, in misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93397:22"/>Libertinisme, and excursions from the former strictness and severity of life; nor of the other hand, under the pretence of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Justice to the body, and the demands of Nature, to lash out into excess and riot, Discretion is that which in the Gospel is call'd the Eye and the Light of the body, which our Saviour sayes, if it be single the whole body shall be full of light, but if evil the whole shall be full of darkness, for this being the Guide and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector of all our actions, if it been't forcified with a true Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and an exact Wisdom, the whole Man shall be overrun with error and vice, for it self being dark and blind, it necessarily follows that all that depends upon it's directions, must be subject to the utmost ruin and miscarriage, to this purpose, and with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of all, spake the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93397:23"/>Angells, who was well verst in all the various arts of Satan to ruin Virtue, and to overset a well-meaning, but an imprudent Zeal and Religion. Thus spake he, who had grappled with him alone for so many Years together in the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful conflicts of the Desart, who had observ'd all the turnings, and windings of the Serpent, and who was throughly skild in the policies and strength of the adversary; and whoever considers the Nature of Religion, and the designes of the Enemy, and his own weakness, will quickly allow that there is nothing to be done, that will last long, and endure to the end, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the utmost assistance of this Virtue of Prudence, that must at the same time oversee the work of Religion, and keep an Eye on the Enemy, thats alwaies attack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us with stratagem and force, with Power and Address, and has
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93397:23"/>made such miserable Breaches in the greatest Men, that seem'd to be the Forts and Bulwarks of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, how has he power'd in Ruin upon them, on the first dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of a weak place, and the works that were so long a rear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and with so much pains carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, on a suddain demollisht and thrown down, or so miserably shat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, and broke, that nothing but the Infinite Mercy and Goodness of God, whose Compassions never fail, and of whose Goodness there is no end, could ever repair them again, and who is alwaies ready to the assistance and deliverance of those Faithful Souldiers that fight Manfully in his service, tho they fall they shall not be cast a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, for the Lord supporteth and raiseth them with his pitty, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as a Father pities his own Son.</p>
            <p>But a spiritual prudence with the assistance of the Spirit of God
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93397:24"/>would have prevented the wound, and fore bruise, and the sad fall, would have kept the happy Man, still happy in an uninterrupted joy, in a clear view of Heaven, and in the direct road to it: a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prudence would have prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the labours and the sorrows, the Travel and the Throes of a bitter repentance, that's like the setting of a broken arm, or a hard Escape after a shipwrack, or the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Man in the Gospell, that was left half deaad on the road by the Highway-men, we can not be too circumspect against our own weakness, and against the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riness and strength of the Enemy, who is alwaies awake, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting, and acting, who never grudges us his malice or his pains, who alwaies stands in the dark to us, and we in the light to him, who has the parts of an Angel, and the wickedness of what he is,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93397:24"/>whose skill in holy things is great, and use of them execrable, while he plaid the Scriptures against <hi>Jesus</hi> and batter'd him, as it were, from Heaven, and no doubt but he often takes our ruin too out of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, who have not that infinite presence of mind to answer and stun him, that <hi>Jesus,</hi> who is God blessed for ever, had, who thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd upon him out of the same Scriptures, which he had pollut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and desecrated by quoting 'em to such desperate and infernal pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses; and our Holy Saviour, our Infinite Friend, the Captain of our Salvation, the Great Leader and General of the Christians, seems to have given way to the Tempter, only to instruct and discipline his Souldiers in the Arts of foiling him, to teach them how to grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the Powers of Darkness, and to return Scripture for Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and while he endeavours
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93397:25"/>to poyson us out of the very Fountains of Life, to give him of the same Waters till he burst, and to assert their Holy meaning while he debauches them with his Gloss, and while he is flying the fiery Darts at us, to cut him down with the Sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is the Word of God, praying alwayes with all Prayer and Supplication in the Spirit, and crying out to the God of Help, who is mighty to save, and who views the Battle, and pitties our wounds, and binds them up himself with the Bowels of a Father, and then Crowns us with Garlands and Joys, with Lawrels and Glory; and when we have sufficiently sweated and bled, translates us to Palaces and everlasting Kingdomes, where the Martyr bleeds no more, and where the secret and unprais'd Labours of the Confessor are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulg'd
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93397:25"/>and crown'd, in the presence of Myriads of flaming Spirits, who congratulate his humble and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quish'd miseries, while the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Martyr ascended to Heaven, born up by Acclamations and Triumph, and had a quicker passage into the Bosom of Glory, and the Mansions of Rewards, and to the General of his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who saw him fighting and dying in his Cause, and expire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the Banner of the Cross, and deputed Angels to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and conduct his Glorious Soul to lire and Triumph for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in the Kingdomes of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:93397:26"/>
            <head>Of the Advantages of the Great, in Respect of Religion and its Rewards.</head>
            <p>WHen I consider the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Immortal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of Vertue and Religion, I cannot but conclude them happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, who are in the best circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances for obtaining, (by the Goodness and Mercy of God) the largest share of them, such as Kings and Princes, and those who act in the most eminent Stations under them, whose Examples may turn Millions to Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and themselves shine as the Stars for ever and ever, for setting the happy Example by the Grace of God given them, without which no man whatsoever can live, or move, or have his Being, as a Christian.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93397:26"/>
            <p> What shall I say of <hi>Theodosius</hi> the Emperor, and to what shall I equal his Glory, and his Life, so full of Triumph and wonders, who was perfect Emperor, and perfect Hermit; right Ancient Roman, and right Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian: <hi>Claudian</hi> says he was too much belov'd of Heaven, and that the Winds and the Seas were confederate to his Glory, and better Historians than a Poet say, the Stars in their courses fought against his Enemies, and that the Winds blew under his Banners, and serv'd under him in Storms, and swept the Foe, like that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient River of <hi>Kishon.</hi> He was in Battle like a destroying Angel, and in private Fasted and Prayed like a Saint.</p>
            <p>The following Memoir of him, if not authentick, yet is very enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining. 'Tis said a certain Hermit had liv'd forty years in the Desart, retir'd wholly from the World,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93397:27"/>and applying himself with great care and earnestness to the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Soul, a desire at length enter'd into his mind to know if any exceeded him in humble Mortification, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he desir'd God to reveal it to him, that he might follow his Example and 'twas answer'd him that the Emperor <hi>Theodosius,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding that he was Master of the greatest Glory in the World, was not inferiour to him in Humility, or in overcoming himself. The Hermit with this answer, repair'd to the Imperial Court, where he had easie access to the Courteous and Religious Emperor, to whom the Servants of God, such as were famous for sanctity of life, were alwaies welcome, not long after he found means to speak to him, and to know his secret Religious Life, and his Holy Exercises.</p>
            <p>At first he only acquainted him
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93397:27"/>that he gave large Alms, that he kept under his Body by discreet austerities, that he observ'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial Chastity, and that he caus'd Justice to be distributed exactly. These things seem'd well to the Hermit, especially in so great a Man, but still humbly thought he had gone as far himself, if not farther; for he had renounc'd all, and given away all he possest for the sake of Christ, which he thought was more then to give part in Alms, he never knew woman in his life, which he thought was more then the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servance of Conjugal Chastity, he never did injury or injustice to any, which was more than to cause it to be kept towards others, his abstinence from what ever was pleasant or delightful, was continual and uninterrupted, which he modestly judg'd was
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93397:28"/>then to abstain and mortifie at certain times, so that something unsatisfi'd at this account, he humbly importun'd the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to conceal nothing from him, and that it was the Divine will he should do so, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror thus importun'd, said to him. <q>Know then that when I assist at the Horse Courses, and other Entertainments in the Circus where my presence is expected, I so withdraw my mind from those glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vanities, and Enemies of true happiness and wisdome, that though my Eyes be open, and <hi>I</hi> seem to look on them, yet I see them not, but em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy my self inwardly and secretly in the midst of so much shew and noise, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Crowd, on objects much greater and happier, and that exceed all the vain
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93397:28"/>and melancholy noise, &amp; glory, and shew of this World; with Glories and Happinesses which the giddy and uncertain Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple neither gave me nor can take from me, and when their Entertainments are at an end, mine are not, but rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd and enlarg'd, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of those Enemies of true Joy and Happiness.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Hermit remain'd asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht at this sort of Desart, and at this sort of Mortification, which he readily granted was beyond all his life, and any thing he could pretend to.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Know also said the Emperor that I live by my Labour, for I transcribe certain parchments in a fair hand, which being sold the price pays for my food.</q> With this Example of Poverty in the midst of so great riches, and such Temperance in the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93397:29"/>midst of so much affluence, that under Purples and Empire, and all the Labours and Tryumphs of the war, and the harder tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of a soft, and treacherous, a luxurious, and dispiriting Peace, he wore the hardships and poverty, the necessities and humility of a private man. The Hermit was perfectly amaz'd, and satisfi'd that the Throne stood as near Heaven as the Desart, and that the wondrous Emperor and he, were about the same business. The Truth of all this in substance is affirm'd to us by the best accounts of this Great Man, who was Good and Courteous as a Seraphim, Humble and Austere, as this or any other Hermit.</p>
            <p>If he surpast this wondrous Inhabitant of the Desart, and at the same fill'd all the duties of an Emperor, a Father and a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93397:29"/>General, who shall doubt to prefer this Man, this Master and Servant, this Lord and Vassal of Mankind, that sweats and bends under the weight of a Crown, and at the same time toils in all the duties of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Christian, to the lonesom Man, that converses only with Angels and Tygers, and eats with the wild Ass and the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard, and sleeps with the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and watches with the Stars, tho he were paler than the Moon, or leaner then an Italian Harlot, or humble as his Cell, or constant to his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as the Rock he lives in to his place, or roar'd in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, like the Waves of the neighbouring Sea, in its hollow bottome: For still he saves and serves but one, and is undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb'd as the Lyon of die Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness, that never hears the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93397:30"/>roar of the Hunter, and beholds he Storm from his Cave in which the World is torn and driven, where he sleeps and wakes like an Inhabitant of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother World, while the Prince and the Publick Man, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and the King toil for the preservation of the World, and ride Admirals in the Storm, and set their Faces against the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest and the Winds, and their hands to the Helm; and while the Hermit is saving his single stake, they are toiling for all Mankind, and are ready to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish themselves to save the World, and the innumerable passengers committed to their care, and if the Hermit prays for the whole World which he has wholly forsaken, so does the Emperour or the Queen, and works in the Storm too, which the Hermit does not,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93397:30"/>that's departed, hugging his Plank, and tryumphing in a single Salvation; while his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are sinking in the Ship he has quitted, and which perhaps his help would have saved.</p>
            <p>Surely Kings and Queens are they, who by turning many to righteousness shall themselves shine like the Stars for ever and ever, they shall rise like the Martyrs from the toils and the labours of Empire, to eternal Crowns, and everlasting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, to Reign and Triumph in earnest, whereas on Earth they were but as the Servants of Mankind, and Ministers of the common Good, they were glorious as Generals and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals, as Governours and Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, under the great Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrator of the World, but the Harvest and the Tryumph is not til death, 'til they are broke
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93397:31"/>with Cares and consum'd with Empire, and crusht into their Graves by the weight of their Crowns and Purples, 'til their hands are gall'd with holding the Scepter as the labouring Mans with the Spade, 'til their Minds are spent into Epilepsis and Appoplexes, and suspensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thought and life, 'til they are consum'd with Counsels and Fears, wîth Watchings and Concern, and at last like St. <hi>Paul</hi> are offered up a Sacrifice on the Service of us all.</p>
            <p>And now what shall I say of the glorious Reward of so much Labour and Martyrdom, of so much Care and Death, such as the storm'd Mariner, nor the bloody Plain ever knew, for their Contentions are fierce but short, and their Labours die in a short strugling, and a few hours, and are presently crown'd
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:93397:31"/>again with Songs and Mirth, with Tabret and Harp, with soft and easie Joys, such as never come near the Throne, or dwell upon the Temples of Kings.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <head>Of true Wisdom.</head>
            <p>HOw much the Wisdom of the World, and true Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom differ may be seen by that expression of Scripture, If any Man in this World seemeth to be wise, let him become a fool, that he may be wise; that is, let him pursue a Wisdom that's quite opposite to that of the World, and is therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted folly by it. That en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of Manageing the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ests of this life to the best ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93397:32"/>and pursuing World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honors and Pleasures, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to despise them all, and to hold Nothing for Our Interest, but Eternal Happiness, Eternal Honour, and Eternal Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and bids us look on the utmost that can be made of this life, as impertinence and loss, as labour and toil to no purpose, as an improveing a less misery to a greater, as a making our selves that with a great deal of Art, and Industry, that we may be by nature, and to our hands.</p>
            <p>And therefore directs us to quite other courses from those of Human Wisdom, it bids us pursue that that will answer our pains, and by Methods, that will Demonstrate our Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, things that will last as long as God, and Heaven, and our Souls, that are as big as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:93397:32"/>our Hopes. and as long as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, that are rational, Clean, and Substantial, that comfort sollidly, and that will outlast a dream, or a fancy, or a mistake, and will be found within and about the Soul, at the end of a Thousand Ages, Warmeing and Transporting, Cherishing and Ravishing it for ever, that outlast the World and all its Pageantry, that are worthy of the Power and Bounty of God, and for which the Son of God Himself endur'd theCross, and despised the shame, and is now set down in the eternal possession at the right hand of the Father.</p>
            <p>Surely this is Wisdom, to propose and compass that that satisfies the thirst of Angels, and then which Fancy and Extravagance can think of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing greater or longer, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93397:33"/>that at the price of the labours of a few Years, and a short Life; it may be a few Daies, or a few Houres, join'd to the Infinite Value of our Saviours Blood, that gives all the value to what we do or suffer, for what can be too Generous for an Infinite Love, or what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence too Great, for the Blood of the Son of God, that was enough to redeem as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Worlds as Men.</p>
            <p>The Honours we secure by the Goodness of God, are to become the Sons of God, and Heirs of God, and Joint heirs with Christ, the Society of Angels, and the Loves of Cherubims, the Embraces of Archangels, and the Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of the Prophets, to behold the Tryumphs of the Martyrs, and our own, if we have suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered (by the assistance of God)
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93397:33"/>much and well, but especially of those that were rackt upon the Throne, and were Tort ur'd in Purples and Ermin, and dy'd of the Publick Good, and of the common Salvation, whom Empires and Care had dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd, and the ingratitude and folly of a rude and giddy People, that regard neither the Honour nor the Labours of a Crown. Such as the First <hi>Charls</hi> of the English, who the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Supplement to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilah</hi>'s History of <hi>France,</hi> (a wise Venetian) says was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern for all Princes, except in his Opinion, for he was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self unreform'd in his. How vast was his Religion? And how great were his Troubles? who can tell his Patience but the Holy Spirit that supply'd it? Whom did he provoke? and how was he provok'd? he forgave
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93397:34"/>the wickedness of his Enemies, while they refuse to forgive his Vertues, he was great, and humble, and Good, and Mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and Holy, and perscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Sic occulos, Sic ille manus, Sic ora ferebat.</hi> And in all things follow'd the Example of his Prince and Saviour, and was Numbred amongst the Transgressors, in his Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his Judgment was taken away, he was taken from Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and from Judgment, and who shall declare his sorrows. He was cut off from the land of the living, he made his grave with the wicked, because he had done no Violence, neither was any deceit found in his Mouth. But he now sees of the travail and of the sorrows of his Righteous Soul, and is satisfi'd for ever, <hi>Et te Catalina minaci pendentem Scopulo, Furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arumque
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93397:34"/>Ora trementem, I Daecius! I, Nostrum! Meliorihus utere Fatis!</hi> shine forth for ever, like the Son in the Kingdom of the Father, let him Tryumph for ever above, with <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> and <hi>Theodosius,</hi> and with our own Most Holy <hi>Edward,</hi> and so great a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression was due to so Great a Memory, who shall make our Histories Mourn, and our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals Sad and Horrid for ever. And they that read his Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy will weep, and Posterity will mourn over so much Mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for no other reason but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he was Holy, and Just, and Good, <hi>&amp; Servantissimus ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return, True Wisdom will direct us to the proper means, for the securing the Highest Ends, 'twill labour with us, and be with us, 'twill
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93397:35"/>enable us, and assist us, 'twill Direct and Conduct us, and at last Enstate us in the Eternal Glories we pursu'd, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, we shall dwell upon every folly, and run after every mistake, and obey our Fancy, and miss both our way and our End. We shall pursue our ruin with labour and sorrow, and walk in darkness and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and every step will be a fall, and every fall a bruise, and we shall tumble from one precipice to another, till at last, we have accomplish't our sorrows, and perfected our ruin. But True Wisdom , which is the Gift of God alone, will secure us from all this misery and folly, and will lead us through Happiness to Happiness, through a Glorious Way to a Glorious End, for her ways are ways of Pleasant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93397:35"/>and all her paths are peace, she is a Tree of life to them that lay hold on her, Happy is every one that retaineth her, she is more Pretious than Rubies, and the Things Thou canst desire, are not to be compared unto her.</p>
            <p>As many as are the ruines that attend on Vice, so many are the deliverances we receive from Wisdom, that's to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to Scepters and Thrones, and in comparison of which riches are of no esteem, and all gold in respect of Her, is as a little sand, and silver is no more then clay, She is beyond Health and Beauty, and the Light it self, for the Light that comes from her never goes out, all good things together come with her, and she is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, for she is a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer unto Men that never
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93397:36"/>failes, for thus she speaks of her self in the Book of Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Whatever is Desirable, whatever is Praiseworthy, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is Charming, whatever is Profitable, and Lasting, flows from her, for in her is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding Spirit, Holy, One Onely, Manifold, Subtle, Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Clear, Undefiled, Plain, not subject to hurt, Loving the thing that is good, Kind to Man, Stedfast, Sure, Free from care, Having all Power, seeing all things, and going through all, understanding, Pure and most subtle Spirits, for Wisdom is more moveing than any motion, the passeth and goeth through all things by reason of her pureness, for she is the breath of the power of God, a pure Influence flowing from the Glory of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, therefore can no defiled thing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:93397:36"/>fall into her, for she is the brightness of the Everlasting Light, the unspotted Mirrour of the power of God, and the Image of his Goodness. And being but one, the can do all things, anal remaining in her self, she maketh all things New, and in all Ages entring into Holy Souls, she maketh them friends of God, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, for God loveth none, but him that dwelleth with wisdom, for she is more Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful then the Sun, and above all the Order of Stars, being compared with the light, she is found before it, in that she is conversant with God, she magnifies her Nobility, yea the Lord of all things himself lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her, for she is privy to the Misteries of the knowledge of God, and a Lover of his works, it riches be a possession to be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:93397:37"/>desir'd in this life, what is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher than Wisdom, that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things, and if prudence work, who of all that are, is a more cunning workman then she? and if a man love righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, her labours are Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, for she teacheth Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and Prudence, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and Fortitude, which are such things, as men can have nothing more profitable in this life, if a man desire much Experience, she knoweth things of old, and conjectureth aright things to come, she knoweth the subtilties of spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and can expound dark Sentences, Wisdom is glorious, and never fadeth away, who so seeketh her early, shall have no great travell, to think there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon her, is perfection of Wisdom, and whoso watcheth for her, shall quickly be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:93397:37"/>Care, for she goeth about, seeking such as are worthy of her, sheweth her self favourably to them in the ways, and meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them in every thought. For the very beginning of her, is the desire of discipline, and the care of discipline, is Love, and Love is the keeping of her Laws, and the giving heed to her Laws, is the assurance of incorruption, and incorruption maketh us near unto God. Wisdom was with thee which knoweth thy works, and was present with thee, when thou madest the World, and knew what was acceptable in thy sight, and right in thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, for so the ways of them that liv'd on the Earth were reformed, and Men, were taught the things that are pleasing to God, and were saved through Wisdom
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:93397:38"/>thus Wisdom of her self, whose fetters are a strong defence, and whose chains are a Robe of Glory. For there is a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Ornament upon her, and her bands are purple lace, thou shalt put her on as a Robe of honour, and put her about thee as a Crown of Joy: And thus the Son of <hi>Syrach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What can now be thought of? what can be desir'd? What can be wish't for that Wisdom does not in abundance supply us with? The Treasures of both Worlds are from it, Temporal and eternal joys, Peace and Love, the Rest and Triumph of the Soul, Security and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Hope and everlasting Fruition, Crowns, and Scept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Kingdoms, Defence and Strength, Libertie and Power, Victory and everlasting Extacies.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:93397:38"/>
            <head>Of a Virtuous Obstinacy.</head>
            <p>HE who can count the Ruines that flow from a weak and mischievous Civility, from the preferring a Ceremony before our Souls, and being Complaisant to being sav'd, may count the Advantages that flow from a Wise and Noble Rigor, from a Manly and Christian severity of Manners, of Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of Religion, that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures our wise designs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects what we have begun, and bears down the World and it's follies, and brings the Wise Man safe to his Port, thro' Storms and Calms, thro' Rocks, and Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, and Sands, thro' a false and an Outragious World, thro' Flatteries and Threats, thro' Custom, and Fashion, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:93397:39"/>discouragement, that shews us the value and disvalue of every thing, and bids us grasp the former like Death, and pursue with Resolution, and persist undaunted and unwearied, and force our way thro' a Distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd Age, and a Disorder'd World, with the Courage of Soldiers, that would rather dye then not overcome, that Trains us to the hardest Grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and bids us declare eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal war against Easiness and Follie, and to Dispute it to the last, when attack'd with Strength and Rage, rather then surrender our Interest and our happiness, or Deliver up our Souls and our heaven, or if becalm'd with pleasures, and weaken'd by temptation, it alarms all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Soul, and throws off the soft ruin, and frights the treacherous happiness, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:93397:39"/>Joy, and bids the Soul be strong and firm in its Interests, and Resolute and obstinate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>against the Betrayer and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vader, and assert the Powers of Wisdome and Fortitude, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Force, or Mine, against the Pestilence that walks in darkness, or the Arrow that flies by day, and neither will suffer its Power to be delivered into Captivity, nor its Beauty into the Enemies hand, but makes it rouse like a Giant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresht with Wine, and put its e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to a perpetual shame, it rejects the snare, and the Treaty, and the Temptation, and will take nothing in Exchange for the Soul.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:93397:40"/>
            <head>Of Peace.</head>
            <p>WHO can speak to the Vallue of this Virtue? who can tell how much the Happiness of Heaven it self consists in't? the Angels pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it on Earth at the Birth of our Saviour, and he pour'd it out again in a double Effusion a little before his death, my Peace I give unto you, my Peace I leave with you. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is a friend to Mankind, whoever wishes well to the World, will admire and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote this Blessing and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, the balm of Societies, the the Joy of Kingdomes, the Blessing of Nations, the Resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of Order, and the Preserver of the World.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:93397:40"/>
            <p> Oh execrable War? that stainest the Ocean and the Land, that scatterest horror and groans, and travail'st with desolation and death, that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test the World in Arms and Misery, by thee are we robb'd of that sacred blessing of Peace, and by thee depriv'd of the many blessings that flow from that one. By thee the Nations are divided, and Kingdoms torn, from thee is toil, and misery, sorrow and travail, a labouring and Ambitious mind, and a frighted Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that turn'st the peaceful, World into a Howling Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, from thee are Rivers of human blood, and by thee the City is a Forrest, and the Prince falls like a Lion or a Tiger, before thee fly Order, and Government, Joy and Peace, and Mirth and Innocence,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:93397:41"/>and a good Conscience, and in thy hydeous train and follow, go Murders, and Spoil, and Fire, the weeping Widow, and the expos'd Infant, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther slain by the Son: and which is more execrable, the friend by his friend, the Captive and the miserable Prince, and the Holy Man bound, flaming Altars and Blasphemy: and the troubled, and the Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tirant, marching slow and heavy, gloomy and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, with a load of guilt and horror, for the blood and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness of the World.</p>
            <p>Therefore O Sacred Peace of Mind and Societies, how shall we sufficiently prize thy blessings, by which the Nations flourish, and from which there is Joy over the World? that makest the single man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, and Mankind to triumph,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:93397:41"/>that filleth the breast with content, and the World with blessing, that Restoreth Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Order, and turneth the Forrest into a Kingdom, and Armies into Commonwealths, and in the place of the Lawrel and Oak, planteth the Vine and the Olive, and turneth the Tyrant and the General, into Magistrates of Peace, and the Oppressors into Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: That breaketh the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of the Bow, the Shield, the Sword, and the Battle, and by whom all the Men whose hands were mighty, have found nothing. They shall prosper that Love thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:93397:42"/>
            <head>Of Contemplation, and the Active Life.</head>
            <p>IN these two Charmels run all our Happiness, in the one we behold, in the other we serve him whom our Souls love, in the first we gaze on his beauties, and contemplate his Glory and Majesty, his Power and Love, his Greatness and Condescention, his Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency and Eternity; in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we exert our Creations, and act our Beings, and do what we were made for, and minister to the Glory of the Almighty, we do good, and are blest, and offer the Sacrifice with which God is so much pleas'd, we serve in our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:93397:42"/>and lay hold on Eternal life. The first somtimes raises us up to Heaven, and somtimes brings down Heaven to us, and is the union of both Worlds, and enlarges the Soul, which by it often mounts to Heaven, notwithstanding the weight and encumbrance of the body, and views the Eternal Palaces of Glory, and the Mansions of the Blest, and the Ineffable Glories of Jesus, the Redeemer and Saviour of the World, who died and is risen again, and is set an the right hand of the Father; by the latter we serve Mankind, and labour in the works of Charity, and entertain strangers, and somtimes Angels, and add to our Faith, Works, and make our Religion profitable and use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that others are the betrer for our Christianity, and the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:93397:43"/>Age we live in, and while we ensure our own Salvation, we endeavour that of others too, our labours are common, and we aim at the good of all, as well as of our selves, we are Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and Publick, Noble and enlarg'd, Good and Kind, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving that every one may be as happy as our selves, and placing our own happiness in the felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of others, enlarging their Joys, an lessening their mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and abating their sorrows, and endeavouring that all the World may be as easie as our selves, and the single man is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for the whole humane Nature, and the private man for the Common-wealth, and becomes a Father to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and a Common-Good, and the Servant of Virtue, and a Friend to Religion, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes its Interests, and blesses
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:93397:43"/>Mankind, and the Worlds his family, and his great design, is the common Salvation, and the perfect and eternal happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of all, that humane Nature may rejoyce, and that Religion, and Virtue, and life, might o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verspread the whole World, and that sin and misery, vice and ruin, might be banisht for ever, here he labours, here he swears, here he toils, and for this great end, he sacrifices his rest and ease, his private Interest and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and in the accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, is abundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenc'd.</p>
            <p>By Contemplation we sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the end of our labours, and in the Active life, we perform them, by Contemplation we taste the eternal Joy, and dwell for a while in Heaven, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse with Angels, as this body will endure, as this imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:93397:44"/>Life will permit, and in the Active life, we perform the Conditions to which so great rewards are promis'd, and sight the Battels, that are Crown'd with eternal Victories and wreaths, with Lawrels and Heaven; and discharge those duties, that secure our everlasting happiness, and by patient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in well doing, seek, and at last obtain Glory, honour, Immortality, and eternal Life.</p>
            <p>In the Contemplative Life we converse with our selves, and our hopes, with the purest No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of virtue and happiness, and the Soul often entercourses with Angels, and I suppose chiefly with him thats apointed for her Guard, and for her Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector, and whether she will or no, with the evil Spirits, that are always arguing in the behalf of vice, and soliciting to ruin,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:93397:44"/>by a thousand falacies, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thusiastick Delusions, with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and Philosophy siner then any is taught, or learnt in the Schools, by Images and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas, that Court and Charm e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the forcing of the corrupt will; and great is their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from their immaterial and Spiritual Natures, by which they joyn the Soul in closer ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and when the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is weak, the Impulse is strong, and the Delusion, repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and immodest, and the chief seat of the mind is attackt with strength and Violence; and if Ignorant or Infirm, is quickly overcome; but chiefly is the Soul attackt, by one single Spirit, that uncessantly solicits its ruin, and spares neither Arguments, nor pains, nor Industry, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat its happiness, and the Care of the good Angel, that watches
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:93397:45"/>as uncessantly for its security and one of the great advantages of Meditation is to defeat the Stratagems and the falacies of the Spiritual enemy, of whose wiles St. <hi>Paul</hi> himself had large expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and trouble, for there is in them, the subtlest address, the deepest pollicy, the slyest Insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation, the most moving Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the strongest Ideas and perswasions; finer then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in Oratory, and arguments subtler then any in Phylosophy.</p>
            <p>In the Active life, we follow the great President, who went about doing good, whose life was Charity, and who dy'd of Love, and who has declar'd his Religion is nothing but love, and shewing it, and has given the highest honours to those that have most of it. God is Love, and he that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:93397:45"/>God in him, are the words of the Greatest Lover that ever was, by whose Love the World stands out of Eternal flames, for he di'd for that end, and by whose Love, and by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Sufferings of whose Love, the World hopes for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting Bliss, and he who best follows this Glorious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, takes the best means to secure this Everlasting Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and lives more like the Holy Jesus, then any Hermit or Monk in the World, for he like the Holy Jesus, labours in the common good, and is not satisfi'd with a private Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and he prays and meditates as well as the Hermit too, for so may a General in the very A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony and doubt of the Battle, and a Prince in the midst of Councel, and the labouring man in the sweat of his toyl.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:93397:46"/>
            <head>Of Prayer.</head>
            <p>WHoever considers the Attributes of God, and reflects that he is all Power, all Goodness, by his Grace, can scarce cease from a constant address to the Infinite Object. For in him is an Infinite Sourse of help, an unexhausted Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, an endless Mercy, that drowns the offence, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the Offender, and charms him by patience into a better life, and stronger Vows, and Humbler and Sincerer Addres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; his Glory draw; the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the whole World, which is one Common Prayer, and a united, secret, Constant Devotion of the whole Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:93397:46"/>Adoring the Creating Power, and blessing the Mercy of the Upholding Power, that pardons Iniquity, Transgressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Sin, that's slow to Anger, and of Infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. That made the Man, and therefore lets the sinner live, till he repents, to live for ever: The unlimited Mercy of the Infinite Being, draws a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Prayse, and Love, from all the Creatures he has made and preserved; he is always blessing, and 'tis our duty to be alwayes praising him, his Love has no bounds, nor ought our Zeal and Affection to him have any; such Infinite Beauty and Perfection, ought to be attended with endless Vows and Address, with the incessant Sacrifice of Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Love, and such a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diness and Power to assist and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:93397:47"/>help, must needs be throng'd with Altars and Devotion.</p>
            <p>But is there any greater Joy and Honour than Prayer? when the Sinner approaches the presence and mercy of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, to be Caress'd and Forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to be pardon'd and resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r'd, and to be cloth'd with the Garments of Joy, instead of the Garments of Vengeance, and the Spirit of Heaviness, what Honour Equal to that of talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Almighty? and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing answerd by the Eternal, to be admitted into an Infinite Presence, to expose our mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and declare our wants, and to intreat for succors and aid, while Millions of Angels are present at the Address, and are concern'd at our wants, and our guilt, and rejoyce at the Bounty and Mercy of the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal King, though they can't but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:93397:47"/>with astonishment cry out, what is man that thou art mindful of him.</p>
            <p>By Prayer we Cancel the terrible debt of sin, that lies heavy on our Salvations, and presses down our Souls to the neathermost Hell; but all through the Merits and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of the Eternal Son, and Holy Spirit; by Prayer we rise from the Hell of guilt, and the Furies of Despair, to the peace of God, and to the Hope of Sons and Heirs, and to the rapturous expectation of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Bliss; from Tears and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to Halelujahs, and Victory, and Praise; from trembling at his Justice, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in his mercy, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing in his Salvation.</p>
            <p>By Prayer we triumph over the Powers of Darkness and Hell, and overcome in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:93397:48"/>of Temptation, and resist even unto blood striving against sin; by Prayer we bind the Evil Spirit, and avoid the Pestilence that walks in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and go upon the Lion and the Adder, the young Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Dragon, and shun the Arrow that slies by day; it opens and shuts the Heavens, and Casts the Battle, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stores Peace, and appeases Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, and blesses the World; by it we proceed in the Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Virtue, and subdue ill habits, and plant good, and become wise, and Holy, and Everlastingly Happy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:93397:48"/>
            <head>Of the many and contradicting Christianities in Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</head>
            <p>MAy they find mercy in that day who first di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Unity of the Faith, and with it destroy'd the bond of peace, and righteousness of Life. I think it reasonable to infer from those words of our Saviour to St. <hi>Paul; Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me!</hi> that he is capable of a holy trouble and concern in his Glorified State, as likewise from the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy of the Head with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and the Members; and if so, what can we imagin our Holy
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:93397:49"/>Saviour to be more concern'd at, then the tearing and rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his most sacred body the Church, into so many sects and madnesses.</p>
            <p>Whoever is a Setter up of new Religions, is a Setter up of new Gods, and whoever does so, is so far from being a Christian, that he is not so much as a <hi>Socrates,</hi> a <hi>Jew,</hi> or a good <hi>Mahometan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To restore the Purity and Unity of the first Christanity, and to take away the scandal of so many Religions, and so little life, would be an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize worthy the greatest Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and the greatest Piety in the World, and of all the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels of Great <hi>Endoxia's</hi> Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mind.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="collection_of_prayers">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:93397:49"/>
            <head>Prayers.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Everlasting Purity and Holiness, gives us such an imitation of thy Perfection, such a compliance with the Example and the words of thy Holy Child Jesus, such a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence with the Inspirations of the Holy and eternal Spirit that we ma please thee in all things through Jesus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Infinite Beauty and Love, O Boundless Mercy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion, Charm us with thy Beauty, enflame us with thy Love, astonish and convert us with thy Patience, and through
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:93397:50"/>him who offer'd himself on the Altar of the Cross, bring us to thy Glories.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O our Saviour, O our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, grant that we may live so as that thou maist see of the travel of thy Soul and be sati<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied Hear us by thine Agony and bloody sweat, by thy Cross and Passion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Eternal Spirit, by thy pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and inutterable Intercessions, cleanse our Bodies, raise our Souls, purifie our Natures, strengthen our Reason, enlarge our Hopes, confirm our Faith, inflame our Charity, and make our Lives answerable to our Faith, and to the great and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Promises, who art In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite as the Father and the Son.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:93397:50"/>
               <p>O Holy Blessed, and Infinite Spirit, eternal Comfortor, Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Regeneration and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, enable us to know thy motions, and to obey them, and to know the counterfeit motions of evil Spirits, and to resist them, restore one Baptisme, fill us with thy fruits, adorn us with thy Gifts, and hear us by thy Coming and Descent, and by the groans of thy Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O holy, sacred, and Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible Trinity, be Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the whole Creation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate Error and wickedness, enlarge the bounds of the Gospel give it the uttermost parts of the Earth for its Possession, but especially those who have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:93397:51"/>its Purity, and destroy'd its power, and Ʋnity. Let its Dominion be from the one Sea to the other, and from the River to the Worlds end, let its Course be swift as the Suns, and let it travell with a brighter Glory, and let its Empire hold with the World.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="thanksgiving">
            <head>A Thanksgiving.</head>
            <p>E<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernal Father, give us all such a sense of thy Infinite Goodness, that we may thank thee as we ought, and praise thee uncessantly, and love thee with our lives, accept the general Thanksgiving of the World, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ours in particular, blessing
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:93397:51"/>thee for thy self, for the Son of thy Love, for the effusion of the eternal Spirit, for the united Glories, and the confederate Goodness of the Holy and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable Trinity, that conspir'd to our Redemption, and abandon'd the Angels. For the life of Jesus in the flesh, for the Holy Religion he gave, for the Infinite value of his death, and for the Triumphs of his Resurrection, and for the coming of the Holy Ghost. To thee be all praise and Honour Obedience and Love for ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="collection_of_maxims">
            <pb facs="tcp:93397:52"/>
            <p>VErtue alone is Heaven, and Vice is Hell.</p>
            <p>Alive we are damn'd, or with the Happy dwell.</p>
            <p>As we in Vice or Vertue do excel.</p>
            <p>Here we are blest or curs'd, if vertuous crown'd,</p>
            <p>Tho poor, if vitious curst, tho Crowns abound.</p>
            <p>Rouse then my frighted Soul! and obstinately wise,</p>
            <p>Reject the Ruin, and secure the Prize.</p>
            <p>No more of sacred Vertue or of Faith dispute,</p>
            <p>Thy Breast confirms the first, of th'last, the Creed confutes thy doubt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93397:52"/>
            <p> The short, plain, Apostles Creed is all thy Faith;</p>
            <p>Live and Believe, is all the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture saith.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>